Well, all right. Before we move on to
reconstruction, we have to talk about
Abraham Lincoln's boss level leadership
during the Civil War and how it impacted
the way we think about American ideals.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay,
let's begin by talking about how Abraham
Lincoln successfully shifted the meaning
of the war and the effects that it had.
So, remember that Lincoln was a
Republican and as such he had a
significant strain of free soil ideology
right inside of him. What I mean is
during his campaign, Lincoln articulated
his clear belief that the president had
no power to abolish slavery where it
already existed. And so, when the Civil
War broke out, Lincoln understood the
meaning of the conflict as merely
constitutional. In other words, if you
had asked Lincoln in 1861 what the war
was for, he would have said to save the
Union. And you can see that plain as day
in one of Lincoln's letters from 1862 to
a newspaper editor named Horace Greeley.
Lincoln said that if he could restore
the Union without freeing a single
enslaved person, he would do it. Or if
he could restore the Union by freeing
some or all enslaved people, he would do
that. The point is emancipation was not
Lincoln's motivation to win the war. He
aimed to save the Union with or without
slavery. Oh, and by the way, if you want
no guys to follow along with this video
and all my videos, check that link in
the description. Anyway, by the end of
1862, Lincoln had flipped entirely on
that position and made a significant
step to articulate a new reason for
fighting the war, namely to eradicate
slavery. So, what, my dear Lincoln,
changed? Well, two big developments
really contributed to it. First was the
issue of contrabands. And allow me to
Heim explain that one up for you. Now,
in 1861, as Union forces were stationed
in Virginia, three enslaved black people
who had escaped their plantations
entered the camp seeking asylum. And so,
because of mounting pressure from the
abolitionist movement, General Benjamin
Butler declared the three black people
to be contrabands, which by definition
refers to property that can be legally
taken from the opposing side during
wartime. Now, normally this refers to
objects like papers or weapons or
valuable items, but certainly not
people. Like if people are taken during
war, that means they're hostages. But
given the South's insistence on
classifying the enslaved as chattel or
property, Butler decided to use that
against the South and hold their
property in Union possession. I mean, it
was kind of brilliant and deeply sassy
at the same time and I am here for it.
Anyway, it wasn't long before word
spread and thousands of escaped blacks
were arriving in Union camps as
contrabands seeking their freedom. And
by the end of the war, something like
400,000 enslaved people had escaped
enslavement and crossed Union lines for
protection. However, the political
status of these contrabands eventually
became a problem. You see, federal law
justified not returning these black
refugees precisely because they were
property and thus could be legally
classified as contraband. And that led
to the second and related reason that
Lincoln shifted of the war, namely
pressure from radical Republicans in
Congress. Now, since Congress was almost
entirely devoid of pro-slavery
representatives, a staunchly
anti-slavery group known as the Radical
Republicans took control. And they aimed
to destroy slavery as a means to weaken
the Confederacy and strengthen the
future of free labor in the Union.
Therefore, they passed two confiscation
acts, which formally emancipated the
multitude of contrabands that had fled
to Union camps. And to be clear, that
declaration of freedom only applied to
areas occupied by the Union, which would
lay the groundwork for the Emancipation
Proclamation, which I'm going to tell
you more about in a moment. Anyway,
Southerners, not surprisingly, got all
kinds of cranky when these laws passed.
But southern crankies aside, the
legislation for sure had its intended
effect. As more and more enslaved people
escaped, the chief labor source for
southern plantations became thinner and
thinner, which put enormous strain on
the southern economy. And so, the
Radical Republicans proved that
emancipation could actually be a good
strategy for winning the war. So,
therefore, in response to those two
developments, Lincoln pondered adopting
the same tactics in the executive
branch. But Lincoln was far more
hesitant to reframe the meaning of the
war than were the Radical Republicans in
Congress. And Lincoln had his reasons,
but chief among them was that he could
not afford to alienate the slave states
that had remained in the Union. Wait,
what? Did you just say there were slave
states in the Union? That is indeed what
I said, my confuzzled pupil, and I can't
believe this is the first occasion I've
had to mention it, but, you know, here
we are. Yes, it's true. There were in
fact four slave states that did not
secede from the Union, and they were
known as the border states, namely
Kentucky, Maryland, Missouri, and
Delaware. And then West Virginia came
along later, but, you know, whatever.
And we don't really need to get into all
the reasons that they remained within
the Union, just need to know that
Lincoln thought that if he lost these
states to the Confederacy, well, then
the Union might as well pack up and go
home because the war would be lost. And
then adding to the pressure, public
sentiment in the Union was not
altogether on board with abolition. This
was especially true of a faction of
Democrats who constantly pushed Lincoln
to end the war even if the peace was
premature. And those folks were dubbed
Copperhead Democrats by Republicans
since they viewed their policies as
utterly poisonous to the war effort. So,
the point is Lincoln had to walk a very
delicate line when he was considering
reframing the war as a battle against
slavery. Even so, by 1863, the
contraband issue and the confiscation
acts, not to mention the Union victory
at the Battle of Antietam, convinced
Lincoln to issue the Emancipation
Proclamation, which declared that all
enslaved people located in states
currently in rebellion were immediately
and forever free. And don't miss the
nuance there. Lincoln's proclamation
freed all enslaved people in the
Confederacy since those were the states
in rebellion, but freed precisely no
enslaved people in the border states
since they were not in rebellion. But
really follow the logic all the way down
with me. The Confederates had their own
constitution and their own laws, and
they had no obligation to comply with
the proclamation. So, Lincoln freed all
the enslaved people in places where he
kind of had no legal authority, and he
freed no enslaved people in the places
where he had very legitimate authority.
So, legally, the Emancipation
Proclamation did almost nothing to
change the status of enslaved Americans.
So, you know, what's the big deal? Well,
the big deal is that Lincoln's
proclamation had two very significant
effects. First, by reframing the war as
a fight to eradicate slavery, all
southern hopes of allying with Great
Britain and France were dashed. You see,
these countries themselves had abolished
slavery earlier in the century, and it
would just be a bad look if they now
allied with the Confederacy in order to
preserve slavery there. But also,
remember in the last video I mentioned
that the Confederacy believed that they
had a massive bargaining chip to rope
Britain and France into supporting them,
namely cotton. Yes, it was true that
Great Britain imported metric buttloads
of southern cotton to feed their textile
factories. And southern planters
believed that this kind of cotton
diplomacy would ultimately score them a
very powerful partner in their war
against the Union. But unfortunately for
the South, in 1858, Great Britain went
ahead and claimed India as a colony, and
as it turned out, all the cotton Britain
could ever want, they could grow in
India. So, sorry, Confederacy, no
foreign help for you. But then, the
second effect of the Emancipation
Proclamation was that it encouraged
enslaved people in the Confederacy to
escape their bondage and enlist to fight
with Union troops. However, to be clear,
even if Union soldiers now understood
that their purpose was to eradicate
slavery, that did not mean that they
also wanted equal rights for black
Americans or even to fight alongside
them despite their common purpose. Like,
don't be crazy. that meant that most
black Union soldiers who were formerly
enslaved created their own units for
battle. And one of the first of these
all-black units was the First South
Carolina Volunteer Infantry Regiment,
which was made up of formerly enslaved
escapees from South Carolina and Georgia
and Florida. But let's not forget that
enslaved women also escaped and served
the Union efforts, though, you know, not
as soldiers. For example, Susie King
Taylor had escaped enslavement in
Georgia and fled to Union lines in
Savannah. And there she developed skills
as a nurse and educator and served the
black troops in the First Volunteer
Infantry Regiment. So, all that to say,
Lincoln made huge steps in reframing the
meaning of the war from an effort to
save the Union to a battle to eradicate
slavery, and that had huge consequences.
And in doing that, Lincoln did his best
to unify the nation by demonstrating how
emancipation was actually the
fulfillment of America's founding
ideals. And he did this by means of many
speeches and public addresses, but none
illustrate this effort better than the
Gettysburg Address and Lincoln's Second
Inaugural Address. So, Lincoln delivered
the Gettysburg Address in 1863 at the
dedication of the National Cemetery in
Gettysburg, Pennsylvania. we haven't
talked about it, the Battle of
Gettysburg had led to enormous
casualties and deaths for both sides. In
other words, this ground on which
Lincoln stood illustrated the bitter
division between Americans. But Lincoln
thought that it could simultaneously
become the ground of their unification
and healing. So, he began the speech by
saying that the United States was
conceived in liberty, whose most
fundamental belief was that all men are
created equal. And therefore, this Civil
War was the nation's greatest test to
find out if a nation conceived and born
on such a principle can long endure. And
then Lincoln declares that if the Union
is victorious and slavery is abolished,
then the nation will have passed the
test and fulfilled the principles on
which it was founded, and that a
government of the people, by the people,
and for the people shall not perish from
the earth. Okay, then the second example
of
Address. So, Lincoln was reelected in
1864, and he used the occasion to
deliver a speech as custom dictated. It
was a mere 701 words that likely took
only a few minutes to deliver, but
Lincoln used all the rhetorical power he
possessed to explain the cause of the
war and his hopes to welcome back the
states who had broken the Union. He
affirmed that slavery was a powerful
interest for the southern states, and
that everyone knew that this interest
was somehow the cause of the war. And
that war had lasted longer and become
far more costly than anyone had ever
expected. But even so, he ends with a
striking note of hope and unification.
He says, "With malice toward none and
with charity for all, let us strive on
to finish the work we are in, to bind up
the nation's wounds." And those words
foreshadowed Lincoln's plans for
reconstruction after the war. And I wish
I could tell you that a man who longed
for the nation to heal and was capable
of binding up its wounds would be able
to work toward that end after the war
was done. But here's where I tell you
not so much, and we'll pick that up in
the next video. Okay, you can click here
to watch my other videos from Unit 5, or
you can click here to get my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain fold. I'm glad
you came around, and I'll catch you on
the flip flop. I'm Heimler.